<DataObject xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns="http://sifassociation.org/SpecGen" name="StudentLocator">
  <EventsReported>false</EventsReported>
  <SupportsSIF_Example>true</SupportsSIF_Example>
  <Item>
    <Element>StudentLocator</Element>
    <Description>
      <p>StudentLocator has been upgraded to a set of SIF Zone Services.  It is anticipated that the StudentLocator object will be removed from the next major version of this specification.</p>
      <p>
            This object provides a mechanism for requesting and updating state student identifiers.  While communicated using SIF's request/response
            model, this object is an exception case in terms of how it interacts especially with SIF's query mechanisms (e.g. one wouldn't request
            certain elements be returned from <code>StudentLocator</code>).
            The use of this object is dictated by external use cases and best practices.
          </p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Attribute>RefId</Attribute>
    <Characteristics>M</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>A GUID that identifies an instance of this object. This RefId is a &#8220;transient&#8221; value; that is, it SHOULD be generated by the provider at the time the object is provided in a Response message.  This value MUST NOT be used in a later Request for the object.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="RefIdType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Attribute>IdStatus</Attribute>
    <Characteristics>M</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Communicates the orchestration status for the object.</p>
      <p>
            Because the <code>Cancel</code> and <code>Cancelled</code> values model application behavior and may not be implemented by all systems that are
            otherwise capable of supporting <code>StudentLocator</code> objects, they are optional.
            If the requester (district) receives a <code>Cancelled</code> reply but does not support this functionality, the reply should be ignored without
            taking further action. If the responder (typically state) receives a <code>Cancel</code> request but does not support this functionality,
            it should reply with a <code>SIF_Response</code> where the <code>SIF_Response/SIF_Error</code> element is set to indicate an error.
            The <code>SIF_Category</code> should be set to <code>8</code> (Request and Response) and <code>SIF_Code</code> set to <code>9</code> (Unsupported query in request).
            Note: In this case the <code>SIF_Response/SIF_Error</code> element is used per normal SIF request/response protocol;
            not to be confused with the <code>StudentLocator/SIF_Error</code> element, which is to be used when a student lookup results in a processing error.

          </p>
    </Description>
    <Values>
      <Value>
        <Code>Request</Code>
        <Description>This is a request to the state for an Id. The StateProvinceId element may not necessarily be blank&#8212;if the requesting agency believes they know the student's state-assigned Id, StateProvinceId can be pre-filled for validation by the state.</Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Release</Code>
        <Description>Some states require notification when a student leaves the district. This request, accompanied by a valid StateProvinceId, instructs the state to release the binding between this student and the LEA.. The response should also be qualified "Release."</Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Valid</Code>
        <Description>Marks a response from the state with a valid StateProvinceId. If the Request included a StateProvinceId, the value of StateProvinceId in the response could be different.</Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Ambiguous</Code>
        <Description>Marks a response where the state couldn't uniquely identify the student based on the information provided. The state may respond to the request with a single StudentLocator object marked "Ambiguous" and an empty StateProvinceId. Alternatively, if the district agent supports it, the state response may include one or more StudentLocator objects with candidate matches. Each of these objects would be marked "Ambiguous," and populated per the particular state's policies. StateProvinceId need not be empty in these objects.</Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Resolve</Code>
        <Description>If the state and district choose to resolve ambiguities via StudentLocator, the district might follow up an "Ambiguous" response that included match candidate(s) with a "Resolve" request populated with the information from the match candidate selected by the district.</Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>New</Code>
        <Description>If the state and district choose to resolve ambiguities via StudentLocator, the district might follow up an "Ambiguous" response that included match candidate(s) with a request marked "New" to notify the state that none of the match candidates is appropriate and a new state-assigned Id should be created.</Description>
        <Note>Although used in the context of a Request query, this field conveys information to (and from) the state and typically does not participate in the matching logic.</Note>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Cancel</Code>
        <Description>
          <p>
                A district can cancel a <code>StudentLocator</code> transaction in progress as follows:
                The requester issues a <code>SIF_Request</code> where <code>IdStatus</code> is set to <code>Cancel</code> and <code>@TransactionId</code> is set to the
                GUID of a previous transaction.  This instructs the responder to cancel that transaction in progress.
                If successful, the responder replies with a <code>SIF_Response</code> where <code>IdStatus</code> is set to <code>Cancelled</code>.
                If the <code>TransactionId</code> is invalid, the cancel operation was not successful, or an exception occurred,
                the responder replies with a <code>SIF_Response</code> where <code>IdStatus</code> is set to <code>Error</code> and the <code>SIF_Error</code> element
                describes the error.
                Both sides consider the transaction cancelled.
              </p>
        </Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Cancelled</Code>
        <Description>
          <p>
                A state can inform a district that it has cancelled a <code>
                  StudentLocator
                </code> transaction as follows:
                The responder (typically state) replies to a prior <code>
                  SIF_Request
                </code> with a <code>SIF_Response</code> where <code>IdStatus</code> is <code>Cancelled</code>.
                This informs the requester (typically district) that the transaction has been cancelled for whatever reason
                (usually at the direction of state administrative staff through some application user interface).  The transaction ends.
              </p>
        </Description>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>Error</Code>
        <Description>
              When IdStatus is set to <code>Error</code>, the SIF_Error element provides details about the error.
            </Description>
      </Value>
    </Values>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Attribute>TransactionId</Attribute>
    <Characteristics>M</Characteristics>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="GUIDType"/>
    <Description>
      <p>
            GUID that allows requesters and responders to refer to the same logical StudentLocator "transaction" over more than one
            SIF_Request/SIF_Response exchange.
          </p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>StateProvinceId</Element>
    <Characteristics>M</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>This is the student's state-assigned Id. May be empty in a response where IdStatus is "Ambiguous."</p>
      <p>NOTE: Although used in the context of a Request query, this field conveys information to (and from) the state and typically does not participate in the matching logic.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="StateProvinceIdType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>Confidence</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Confidence score. The main use of this element is when IdStatus equals "Ambiguous" and the state returns one or more* candidate matches. The interpretation is that the information populated in each returned object matches the information in the request to the extent expressed in this score. The matching/scoring algorithms (and resultant values) are defined by the particular state.</p>
      <p>States may also choose to use this element for the district to indicate in the query what score threshold it wants associated with the request.</p>
      <p>*A response marked "Ambiguous" with a single match candidate populated likely means that the Confidence score is below the state's threshold for assignment but above the threshold for creating a new state-assigned Id.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type name="xs:normalizedString"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>LocalId</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>This is the requesting agency's unique Id for the student.</p>
      <p>NOTE: Although used in the context of a Request query, this field conveys information to (and from) the state and typically does not participate in the matching logic.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="LocalIdType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>StudentPersonalRefId</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Requesting agency's local zone GUID of the student's StudentPersonal object.</p>
      <p>NOTE: Although used in the context of a Request query, this field conveys information to (and from) the State and typically does not participate in the matching logic.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="IdRefType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>RequestingAgencyId</Element>
    <Characteristics>OR</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Identification of the agency and/or location requesting the state Id. Optional because the SIF Zone infrastructure may provide adequate information for the state to ascertain the origin of the request.</p>
      <p>NOTE: Although used in the context of a Request query, this field conveys information to the state and typically does not participate in the matching logic.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type name="xs:normalizedString"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Attribute>Type</Attribute>
    <Characteristics>M</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>The functional level of the requesting agency.</p>
    </Description>
    <Values>
      <Value>
        <Code>ESA</Code>
        <Text>Educational Services Agency</Text>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>LEA</Code>
        <Text>Local Educational Agency (District)</Text>
      </Value>
      <Value>
        <Code>School</Code>
      </Value>
    </Values>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>GradeLevel</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>The student's current grade level.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="GradeLevelType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>SSN</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Social security number of the student.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type name="xs:normalizedString"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>Name</Element>
    <Characteristics>OR</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>The name(s) of the student.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="NameType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>Address</Element>
    <Characteristics>OR</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>The address(es) of the student.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="AddressType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>Demographics</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Demographic information about the student. This will typically be the core matching information. Privacy considerations may mean that it is filled differently here than it might be in a local StudentPersonal, but it must include enough to drive the state's matching algorithms.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="DemographicsType"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>Contact</Element>
    <!-- <Characteristics>OR</Characteristics> -->
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>Typically used to provide the state information about a student's parents and legal guardians.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="SimpleContactRelationshipType"/>
    <!-- ContactRelationshipType may have been intended; bare OR, which is inconsistent, with SIF design -->
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>EffectiveDate</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>For Requests, this should match StudentSchoolEnrollment/EntryDate.</p>
      <p>For Releases, StudentSchoolEnrollment/ExitDate.</p>
      <p>NOTE: Although used in the context of a Request query, this field conveys information to the state and typically does not participate in the matching logic.</p>
    </Description>
    <Type name="xs:date"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>StartDate</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type name="xs:date"/>
    <Description>Begin date for a range that is being requested.  Note: In most cases this will correspond to the school entry date.</Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>EndDate</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type name="xs:date"/>
    <Description>End date for a range that is being requested.  Note: In most cases this will correspond to the school exit date.</Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>GraduationDate</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="GraduationDateType"/>
    <Description>
      <p>
            Indicates the date the student graduated&#8212;Year, Year and Month, or Year, Month and Day may be specified.
            Intended to facilitate locating students that may not be currently enrolled
            in a school or district, particularly in the context of locating student identifiers for initiating a request for a student's academic record.
            Supplied date values may often be approximations made by the entity endeavoring to request a student's academic record.
          </p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>SchoolAttendedName</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type name="xs:normalizedString"/>
    <Description>
      <p>The name of the school last attended by the student.</p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>SchoolAttendedLocation</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type name="xs:normalizedString"/>
    <Description>
      <p>The location of the school last attended by the student (e.g. city or county name, district name, etc.).</p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>OtherId</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="OtherIdType"/>
    <Description>
      <p>Additional student identifier not represented elsewhere in StudentLocator (e.g. the driver's license number of the student).</p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>SIF_Error</Element>
    <Characteristics>C</Characteristics>
    <Description>
      <p>
            When IdStatus is set to <code>Error</code>, this element provides details about the error.  Rather than the specification
            defining a list of possible error categories and codes for StudentLocator transactions, the SIF_Category and SIF_Code elements may contain
            values defined by the application that is responding to the StudentLocator request.  It is recommended the requester convey these values
            in log files or error reports, along with the SIF_Desc and optional SIF_ExtendedDesc elements.
          </p>
    </Description>
    <Type ref="Infrastructure" name="SIF_Error"/>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>SIF_Metadata</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="SIF_MetadataType"/>
    <Description>
      <p>
            SIF_Metadata/TimeElement may be specified as metadata of a StudentLocator SIF_Request to indicate a time duration to which
            the request parameters apply (as opposed to adding new elements to the StudentLocator object).  This metadata may be supplied by systems
            that know a student existed in a district during a certain time period (e.g. a system initiating a student record exchange).  If the responder
            is able to make use of the metadata, it may do so to narrow down the student look-up; otherwise the metadata can be ignored or logged.
          </p>
    </Description>
  </Item>
  <Item>
    <Element>SIF_ExtendedElements</Element>
    <Characteristics>O</Characteristics>
    <Type ref="CommonTypes" name="SIF_ExtendedElementsType"/>
  </Item>
  <xhtml:Example xmlns="" name="StudentLocator Query">
    <SIF_Message xmlns="http://www.sifinfo.org/infrastructure/2.x" Version="2.5">
      <SIF_Request>
        <SIF_Header>
          <SIF_MsgId>800D2581E7DA4E64AC298CA0ACE51C18</SIF_MsgId>
          <SIF_Timestamp>2006-01-29T16:21:23-06:00</SIF_Timestamp>
          <SIF_SourceId>DistrictAgent</SIF_SourceId>
        </SIF_Header>
        <SIF_Version>2.5</SIF_Version>
        <SIF_MaxBufferSize>8000</SIF_MaxBufferSize>
        <SIF_Query>
          <SIF_QueryObject ObjectName="StudentLocator"/>
          <SIF_ConditionGroup Type="None">
            <SIF_Conditions Type="And">
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>@IdStatus</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Request</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>LocalId</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>123456</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/Gender</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>F</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/BirthDate</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>1989-01-02</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/PlaceOfBirth</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Miami</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/CountyOfBirth</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Dade</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/StateOfBirth</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>FL</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/CountryOfBirth</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>US</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/CountriesOfCitizenship/CountryOfCitizenship</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>US</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>EffectiveDate</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>2003-08-01</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>RequestingAgencyId[@Type="LEA"]</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>98</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>RequestingAgencyId[@Type="School"]</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>1010</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Name[@Type="04"]/LastName</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Doe</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Name[@Type="04"]/FirstName</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Cameron</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Name[@Type="04"]/MiddleName</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>K</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/RaceList/Race[Code="1002"]/Proportion</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>75</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Demographics/RaceList/Race[Code="0999"]/Proportion</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>25</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Contact[Relationship/Code="1735"]/EducationalLevel</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>1050</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Contact[Relationship/Code="1735"]/Name[@Type="04"]/LastName</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Fung</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
              <SIF_Condition>
                <SIF_Element>Contact[Relationship/Code="1735"]/Name[@Type="04"]/FirstName</SIF_Element>
                <SIF_Operator>EQ</SIF_Operator>
                <SIF_Value>Connie</SIF_Value>
              </SIF_Condition>
            </SIF_Conditions>
          </SIF_ConditionGroup>
        </SIF_Query>
      </SIF_Request>
    </SIF_Message>
  </xhtml:Example>
  <xhtml:Example xmlns="" name="StudentLocator Query (SIF_Example)">
    <SIF_Message xmlns="http://www.sifinfo.org/infrastructure/2.x" Version="2.5">
      <SIF_Request>
        <SIF_Header>
          <SIF_MsgId>800D2581E7DA4E64AC298CA0ACE51C18</SIF_MsgId>
          <SIF_Timestamp>2006-01-29T16:21:23-06:00</SIF_Timestamp>
          <SIF_SourceId>DistrictAgent</SIF_SourceId>
        </SIF_Header>
        <SIF_Version>2.5</SIF_Version>
        <SIF_MaxBufferSize>8000</SIF_MaxBufferSize>
        <SIF_Query>
          <SIF_QueryObject ObjectName="StudentLocator"/>
          <SIF_Example>
            <StudentLocator RefId="359D75101AD0A9D7A8C3DAD0A85103A2" IdStatus="Request" TransactionId="A731E63562984A00B02543E87DC5906D">
              <LocalId>123456</LocalId>
              <RequestingAgencyId Type="LEA">98</RequestingAgencyId>
              <RequestingAgencyId Type="School">1010</RequestingAgencyId>
              <Name Type="04">
                <LastName>Doe</LastName>
                <FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
                <MiddleName>K</MiddleName>
              </Name>
              <Demographics>
                <RaceList>
                  <Race>
                    <Code>1002</Code>
                    <Proportion>75</Proportion>
                  </Race>
                  <Race>
                    <Code>0999</Code>
                    <Proportion>25</Proportion>
                  </Race>
                </RaceList>
                <Gender>F</Gender>
                <BirthDate>1989-01-02</BirthDate>
                <PlaceOfBirth>Miami</PlaceOfBirth>
                <CountyOfBirth>Dade</CountyOfBirth>
                <StateOfBirth>FL</StateOfBirth>
                <CountryOfBirth>US</CountryOfBirth>
                <CountriesOfCitizenship>
                  <CountryOfCitizenship>US</CountryOfCitizenship>
                </CountriesOfCitizenship>
              </Demographics>
              <Contact>
                <Relationship>
                  <Code>1735</Code>
                </Relationship>
                <Name Type="04">
                  <LastName>Fung</LastName>
                  <FirstName>Connie</FirstName>
                </Name>
                <EducationalLevel>1050</EducationalLevel>
              </Contact>
              <EffectiveDate>2003-08-01</EffectiveDate>
            </StudentLocator>
          </SIF_Example>
        </SIF_Query>
      </SIF_Request>
    </SIF_Message>
  </xhtml:Example>
  <xhtml:Example xmlns="" name="StudentLocator Response">
    <SIF_Message xmlns="http://www.sifinfo.org/infrastructure/2.x" Version="2.5">
      <SIF_Response>
        <SIF_Header>
          <SIF_MsgId>B0A37581E7DA4E64AC298CA0ACE59CE3</SIF_MsgId>
          <SIF_Timestamp>2006-01-29T16:24:01-06:00</SIF_Timestamp>
          <SIF_SourceId>StateAgent</SIF_SourceId>
          <SIF_DestinationId>DistrictAgent</SIF_DestinationId>
        </SIF_Header>
        <SIF_RequestMsgId>800D2581E7DA4E64AC298CA0ACE51C18</SIF_RequestMsgId>
        <SIF_PacketNumber>1</SIF_PacketNumber>
        <SIF_MorePackets>No</SIF_MorePackets>
        <SIF_ObjectData>
          <StudentLocator RefId="359D75101AD0A9D7A8C3DAD0A85103A2" IdStatus="Valid" TransactionId="A731E63562984A00B02543E87DC5906D">
            <StateProvinceId>98765</StateProvinceId>
            <LocalId>123456</LocalId>
          </StudentLocator>
        </SIF_ObjectData>
      </SIF_Response>
    </SIF_Message>
  </xhtml:Example>
</DataObject>
